<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Examination of severall votes of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament concerning such as take up armes against the Parl. of England or assist in such war wherein is declared that all such persons are traitors by the fundementall lawes of this Kingdome and ought to suffer accordingly.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11208095</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11208095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38977)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Examination of severall votes of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament concerning such as take up armes against the Parl. of England or assist in such war wherein is declared that all such persons are traitors by the fundementall lawes of this Kingdome and ought to suffer accordingly.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Paris and re-printed at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46772:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46772:1"/>
            <head>An Examination of Severall Votes of the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, concerning ſuch as take up Armes againſt the Parl: of <hi>England,</hi> or aſsiſt in ſuch War. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is declared, that all ſuch perſons are Traitors by the fundamentall Lawes of this Kingdome, and ought to ſuffer accordingly, which the <hi>20</hi> of <hi>June 1648.</hi> are Ordered by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, to be Printed and Publiſhed by the Sheriffs in every Market Town.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the many irregularities of the Houſes this Parliament, they have taken up an uſe of printing their Votes, which though of no legall efficacie, yet were the conduits to convey their ſeditious plots to the people, and prepare them by Traiterous ifuſions to aſſiſt their attempts: the force of them depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinng on the reputation of the contrivers: and its ſomewhat likely that the preſent Houſes find ſome diminution of their Authority among the people, and rely on that of their firſt leaders; and therefore they now the 20 of <hi>June</hi> 1648. make uſe of Votes made the 20 of <hi>March</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>It muſt be acknowledged that the 20 of <hi>March</hi> 1642. the People of <hi>England</hi> had a great opinion of the Honour, Wiſdome, and Integrity of the two Houſes of Parliament, upon whoſe words (rather then their own ſence) they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there were things amiſſe in Government, and that from them muſt come the remedy: but they long ſince found how far their actions and deeds differed from their pretences; and now the 20 of <hi>June</hi> 1648. its evident to all of the meaneſt underſtanding, that the burdens of the people are multiplied, &amp; that the moderate Levies of Monies complained of by the two Houſes, to be done by the King, in prejudice of their Liberty, are turned into intollerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions; theſe Houſes ſeeking not to eaſe any grievances, but to gaine power to lay them; and they tell the people by their Actions, that their little finger muſt be heavier then the Kings Loynes.</p>
            <p>The people now ſee, that the reverence and zeal they bare to theſe Houſes, was to a falſe &amp; imaginary deity; and the ſervice they performed to them, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable to God, and odious to all Good men, making their ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters paſſe through the fire, the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to endure all kinde of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to pleaſe this Idoll: They now ſee, that there is no Injuſtice and Oppreſſion equall to that of their two Houſes of Parliament; their Government Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and their proceedings Tyranny, their pretences Hipocryſie, their cruelties and mercileſſe dealings with the King and fellow-Subjects, ſhewing them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inhumane Canibals then Chriſtians; and their multiplyed falſeſhoods and perjuries exceeding the moſt profeſſed deceivers: but it is like they think that the Votes that deceived once, are ſtill of force upon the people, and therefore its neceſſary to diſcover what truth their Votes contain, that are thus relyed on after the many proofs of the uningenuity of thoſe that contrived them. p1 1. We obſerve in the Title, that the Votes have the ſtile of <hi>the Lords &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46772:2"/>Aſſembled in Parliament, concerning ſuch as take up Armes againſt the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>or aſſiſt in ſuch War, wherein is declared, that all ſuch Perſons are Traitors by the fundamentall Lawes of this Kingdome, and ought to ſuffer accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, were the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> the ſtile need not have been varied, but either the Votes might be called the Votes of Parliament, or the War they mention againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, might have been called a War againſt the Lords and Commons; but themſelves well know that the two Houſes are not the Parliament, and then to what end are theſe Votes, for they Vote not that War againſt the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are Treaſon, and War by the King againſt himſelf they intend not.</p>
            <p>But the two Houſes being (vulgarly called the Parliament) to abuſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, have induſtriouſly laboured to implant a belief in them, that the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes without the King, are the Parliament, and that there is a Majeſty in it, and Treaſon may be committed againſt it; and whatever efficacie the Acts of the King in Parliament have, they arrogate to their own Acts without the King; and would have all power (annexed to His Perſon in Parliament, &amp; elſewhere) to belong to themſelves, without, nay, againſt Him, becauſe He exerciſeth His Supreame, power in Parliament: Thus theſe vipers devour their Parent; and being called by the King to be His Councell, (which Title they aſſume in their Declarations) and by the duty of their place to Councell Him only, they moſt Traiterouſly take Councell againſt Him, and Councell His people to Rebell againſt Him, which is the ſumme of theſe Votes; a Treaſon unparalled in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages, and contrary to their former profeſſions and practice; for in all Commiſſions of this Parliment, (deſired by themſelves for the paſſing of Laws) its expreſly affirmed, that no Act or Ordinance of both Houſes, can binds, or be in force without the Kings conſent; and conſequently can be no Act of Parliament, nor can the two Houſes in judgement of Law be the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>In their Barbarous proceedings againſt perſons that have borne Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they have ſtiled their offence a Levying of War againſt the King; and the attempt of Captaine <hi>Burley</hi> to deliver the King out of Priſon, is made by them a Levying War againſt the King, well knowing there is no War elſe Treaſon by Law. And we ask of them, whether the attempt of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> in removing their Speaker <hi>Pelham,</hi> and other Members, and placing <hi>Lenthall,</hi> and others, were not a War againſt the Parliament? it muſt needs be by their grounds, or nothing is; for they made Orders to revoke what paſſed in <hi>Pelhams</hi> time, which needed not, if it were not a Parliament in their ſenſe; and then it muſt follow, that his Excellency is a Traitor by their own rule, and themſelves that aſſiſted him.</p>
            <p>There is no levying War, Treaſon, but ſuch as is made againſt the King, though it be Acted upon His Subjects in Parliament, or in any other capacity; and that which makes a War Treaſon, and againſt the King, is the want of his Command. Mrs. <hi>John</hi> declared in his Speech againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> that levying of War upon the Kings Subjects is Treaſon, for its War againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46772:2"/>Him, and are not they all then Traitors which made this War upon the Kings Subjects, not only upon ſuch as aſſiſted the King, but Neutures? All War that is made upon his dominions, by His Subjects without His Command, is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but its a madneſſe therefore to ſay that a War by His Command is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for then if He be overcome by Rebells, ſuch as aſſiſted Him muſt be Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, for Levying War upon the Kings Subjects: A ſenſleſſe aſſertion, and would make good that ſcoffe at Law, that Victory only makes Traitors; an axiome never owned by Law nor Religion, but drawne from the leud practice of Rebells; the making of War being the Kings peculiar prerogative, and is matter of Supream power, not Juriſdiction, and belongs not to any Court or Counſell, and the two Houſes can claime no more then belongs to a Court or Counſell.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of Commons have Ordered the printing of theſe Votes and tis like they expect Obedience, as if it were an Act of Parliament, though without the King and Lords; Never did one or both Houſes of Parliament preſume to print before this, and we may as well believe they had this Priviledge by the fundamentall Lawes, (which was never known before theſe ſeven yeares laſt paſt) as that the Lords and Commons are the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; or that a War made by the King can be Treaſon. But come now to the Votes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt Vote, that it appears, that the King (ſeduced by Wicked Councell) intends to make War againſt the Parliament, who in all their conſultations and actions, have propoſed no other end unto themſelves, but the care of Kingdomes, and the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all duty and loyalty to His Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemes theſe men had taken ſuch pleaſure in their power of judging, that they fell to judiciall Aſtrologie, and would tell fortunes, for they adventure to tell the intentions of their King, though <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, the Kings heart is unſearchable; doubtleſſe in point of Duty, Subjects ought not to pry into it; and we may ſurely conclude, that as they may be deceived in their conjectures of His intentions, ſo they have certainly broken their Loyalty by making ſuch a Vote, and run into certaine Rebellion upon certaine ſuſpitions; but their caſe is worſe, for they had reſolved (before this pretence) on their violence againſt the King, and had in a great part Acted it, raiſing Tumults againſt Him, Threatning Him with popular furies, unleſſe He conſented to miſchievous Lawes of their contriving; They had Levied an Army for the guarding of Perſons againſt an Accuſation of Treaſon; they had cauſed diverſe Members of both Houſes of Parliament to be aſſaulted &amp; menaced, whereby they were enforced to leave the Houſes, they had ſeized the Navy, diſpoſed the Militia, fortified Townes: and now to blear the eyes of the poor multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, tell them the King intends to make War upon the Parliament; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver King had greater cauſe to right himſelfe, nor ever people leſſe cauſe to make war on him: They would perſwade the people, that if their war be defenſive againſt their King, its lawfull, and if that they ſay its ſo, its then out of queſtion.</p>
            <p>If ſelfe defence be lawfull in Subjects againſt Supreame power, then they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46772:3"/>are not bound to aſſiſt their King againſt Malefactors or Rebels, unleſſe they firſt know the cauſe, whereby all Government is at an end, and obedience muſt follow private perſwaſion, not publique Authority; and the King doth in vaine proclaime an enemy abroad, or Rebels at home, and then he cannot hope long to weare a Crowne; and if Subjects adhere to an enemy, the King may not make War upon them, but firſt ſend for a Judge to Indite them, and a Malefactor may as well uſe force againſt the ſentence of the Judge, upon pretence of Injuſtice; as Subjects againſt their King, upon pretence of want of juſt cauſe of making of War, it being as eſſentiall to Supreame power (which theſe men ſweare to be in the King) as civill deciſions to any Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and if it were not (as moſt certainly it is) the foundation of all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet by Law, and practice moſt undeniably, in the King of <hi>England;</hi> we cannot hope to find modeſty, where we ſee diſloyalty and Rebellion, and in theſe mens reiterated Remonſtrances, they take it for a ground in Law, that the King cannot doe evill, and if the Law will not ſuppoſe he can doe evill, can there be any Law to make Warre upon Him upon pretence of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evill? and if by the policy, and conſtitution of any Kindgome the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Governor be exempt from puniſhment by Law as of neceſſity He muſt, it is a moſt abſurd opinion, that He ſhould be ſubject to private violence; and if the Members of Parliament be corrupt, and entertaine negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with foraigne Princes, their Kings enemies, and adhere to them, as is more then poſſible, and the King declare a Warre againſt ſuch perſons, may they take Armes againſt Him to defend themſelves? then all Rebellions will be ſelfe defences, and none that have force will ſubmit to Law, and ſo it muſt follow, that if any commit Treaſon, the force that the King uſeth for His owne preſervation, or their puniſhment, ſhall be called War againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or War againſt the Subject; but when ordinary wayes of Juſtice are ſhut up by force, the King hath recourſe to His Regall power; and if His Counſell in ſuch a caſe ſhould not adviſe Him to make War upon ſuch perſons, it might well be judged of them, that they were an unfaithfull and wicked Counſell, and though the King had taken no reſolution of War, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great violence offfered Him, as He made appeare by many witneſſes, &amp; reaſons, yet theſe men reproch Him to his face, with theſe Trayterous Votes, and adde, that (the King ſeduced by wicked Counſellors) ſo odious an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the mouths and pens of Subjects, as cannot conſiſt with duty and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and their profeſſions of their care of the Kingdomes, and performance of all duty, and Loyalty to His Majeſties Perſon, ſo contradictory to theſe Votes can get no beliefe, but were deviſed to give colour only to their courſes, being no part of their purpoſes; and theſe Houſes conſiſting of a great number, who for age, education, or parts, being no way qualified to judge of Counſels, and being ſeduced by wicked counſels to reproach their King; and ſeeke His ruine, are no more to be truſted for their care of the Kingdome, (which they have brought to ſhame, impotency, and beggery,) then for performance of their duty to their King, whom they have abuſed with all immaginable contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, depoſed from Government, ſhut up in Priſon, and out of horror of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46772:3"/>guile and fear of puniſhment, have plotted how they may take away his life by poyſon, or aſſaſſination; and theſe ſhameleſſe wretches would have it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that making War upon Him, attempts to kill and depoſe Him, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of Him, and offering of violence to His Perſon, are no Treaſon; but that endeavouring to defend Him, free Him from Impriſonment, preſerve His life are Treaſon; Prodigious impudence, and they might as well Vote He were no King, and that <hi>England</hi> never had a King by Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That whenſoever the King maketh War upon the Parliament, it is a breach of the truſt repoſed in Him upon His people, contrary to His Oath, and tending to the diſſolution of this Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its apparent that the King may juſtly make War upon all or any Members of Parliament for Diſloyall and Traiterous Acts, when ordinary juſtice is ſhut up, and that it is neither breach of truſt repoſed in Him by His people, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to His Oath, nor tending to the diſſolution of this Government; and if the King charge either any, or all of them with ſuch offences, they muſt not ſtand upon their Guard, but ſubmit to legall Triall. Its a known truth they ought to be Tryed by the ordinary Courts of Law, and their owne Votes to the contrary, have neither weight nor credit, being againſt all Law, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not a Malefactor to be his own judge, or to teſtifie in his own cauſe. Its one of the uſuall frauds of theſe men to weakon the opinion and duty of the people of, and towards their King, to tax Him with a breach of Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the People in the King; If they ſhould expreſſe the time when this Truſt was repoſed, their anſwer is that it muſt be ſuppoſed ſo, when the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy was firſt conſtituted; and they ſpeak as if all hereditary Monarchies were no other then elective, and every of them came in upon truſt. A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious piece of Sophiſtry; No doubt all Kings have a duty to performe, and all Subjects hope and pray for their Kings performance of it, but the conſtitution of hereditary Monarchies includes no truſt, but in the frame and conſtitution of that forme of Government, and they in the beginning could not but foreſee that there might come evill Kings, yet they reſolyed not to break the order, but depended rather on Gods providence then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a way to faction and domeſtick broyles, which they eſteemed worſe then the accidentall evill of a ſingle Prince, and which ſtates of another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution often finde by ſad experience; and their imaginary truſt hath no more ground then the proſecution of Traytors by the King hath to be a breach of it, or a War againſt the Parliament; There are duties of parents to children, but they are not truſts; and in hereditary Monarchies, the King is <hi>Rex natus, non datus,</hi> and the people cannot upon pretence of any crime pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, refuſe their admiſſion of Him, much leſſe can they withdraw their obedience for any crime ſubſequent; and as the <hi>Kings</hi> making War againſt all or any Members of Parliament, is no War againſt the Parliament; ſo were it applicable to ſuch a ſence, it were not contrary to any title of His Oath, when he hath ſuch cauſe as was formerly expreſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the diſſolution of Government.</hi> Warre by Princes againſt Rebels is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to preſerve it, but Rebellion againſt the <hi>King</hi> diſſolves all Government,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46772:4"/>for thereby the KING is made a Subject; all His Power deſpiſed, His Subjects Governed by another Power, the ſubmiſſion whereunto is of no leſſe guilt, then to any forrain Power, for it's as deſtructive to that of the KING'S; and we now ſee apparently, all Law, Liberty, and Property is loſt, and all is arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary at the will of Power, and no man by Law or Conſcience bound to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to any Magiſtrate, whoſe power is derived from the KING; and it is an odious uſurpation to uſe a pretended derived Power, when they ſuppreſſe the ſupreme; and the exerciſe of the Soveraigne power by the two Houſes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Commiſſions in the KING'S Name, is all one, as if it were their owne; and if it be Murder to judge to death by Commiſſions in their Names, is it leſſe when they make a Commiſſion in the KING'S? They cannot pretend to have any ſuch Power derived to them, nor can the Kingly power be poſſibly in the two Houſes, for they may differ in Vote, which is a condition the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome cnnnot endure, nor any Law or Reaſon allow; and if theſe men had any thought of that miſery that comes <hi>by diſſolution of Government,</hi> they would not have cut aſſunder all the ligaments of it, ſtriving to get <hi>the King's conſent</hi> to eſtabliſh ſuch a confuſion in this poor Kingdome, as may never be ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in any Generations to come; ſeeking to diſtract the Subjects, and pretend that obedience to them, is loyalty to their KING, though it be againſt Him, and to make Warre for the KING, equally penall to warre againſt Him; Such as make theſe Votes, and ſuch as practice ſuch a Power, are guilty of the <hi>breach of Truſt</hi> repoſed in them by their Countries and Townes that ſent them, of the Oath of Alleagiance and Supremacy taken at their entrance into the Houſe, of all the bloud and miſeries that have inſued from that damnable poſition and practice.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. That whoſoever ſhall ſerve or aſſiſt Him in ſuch Warre, are Traytors by the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, and have been ſo adjudged by two Acts of Parliament, and ought to ſuffer as Traytors,</hi> 11 Ric. 2.1 Hen. 4.</p>
            <p>And why doe they not expreſſe againſt whom it is Treaſon to aſſiſt the KING? they know <hi>there is no Treaſon but againſt the King,</hi> and if they had told all, it muſt cut the throat of their Votes; That Warre by the KING is Treaſon againſt the KING, which is legible onely by theſe bloudy Votes, for if the KING have power to make Warre, He may judge of the cauſe of it; and if He erre in the juſtice of the cauſe, ſuch as aſſiſt Him cannot be puniſhed for doing their duty, which is to aſſiſt Him in any War within the Kingdome, 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. But theſe men ſhould have done well to have told what, or where theſe fundamentall Lawes were, that men might ſee them, and not be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken. If the Statute of the 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. be a fundamentall Law, this is no Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within that Statute. And if 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> be a fundamentall Law, nothing is Treaſon but what is mentioned in that Statute of 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. ſo as if there had been ſuch judgment, as they pretend, the force is wholly taken away. We may not imagine that many of theſe that made theſe Votes underſtood the diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of fundamentall and not fundamentall Lawes, nor that any of them knew ſuch fundamentall Lawes as they herein ſuppoſe, but it was the perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous contrivance of ſome of the Leaders of this rout, to invent words of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46772:4"/>known ſenſe, that they might ſtile any actions crimes againſt imaginary Laws, that were done by any Perſons that they had a mind to deſtroy, and have thereby made the Land guilty of bloud, judging by Laws they know not, and crimes they underſtand not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martyn, Lilburne,</hi> and others, will have fundamentall Law right reaſon, and no reaſon right but their owne; and its moſt probable, the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venters of this terme now in Parliament, had that reſerve to their owne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for none of the Judges (or men learned) could ever yet find what they meant by <hi>fundamentall Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they ſay, <hi>it hath been ſo judged by two Acts, of Parliament, the firſt is,</hi> 11 <hi>of Rich.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>It hath hapned to Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> as is incident to all Aſſemblies, to have ſome, whoſe actions are not for imitation: There are Records of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly and trayterous Aſſemblies in Parliament, and of wicked Decrees made by them; and no honeſt man will think the Judgements or Acts of Parliament in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. touching His Wives and Children, and the many ſad Executions of Innocent perſons, are of Authority; and theſe men have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in this Parliament, <hi>That they hold the Parliament that Depoſed this</hi> Ric. 2. <hi>or any other King, were no lawfull Parliaments,</hi> which muſt be intended in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they were unlawfully called, or their trayterous Acts; and this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 11 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. was aſſembled by a trayterous and prevailing Faction in Warre, as that was, and its Authority was onely Force, and its Acts diſ-loyall and extorted, and were the ground-work of the diſtractions of that KING'S Reigne, and of His trayterous Depoſition and execrable Murder; and theſe Voters chuſe to tread in their ſteps and no man may doubt if they be not prevented, will arrive to the ſame end; and yet ſo deſperate is thein caſe, that it cannot be maintained from this odious example: Theſe men having exceeded the worſt of Traytors, and though they pretend they have not yet killed their KING, it wanted not their will, as appears by the manner of their proceedings againſt <hi>ROLFE,</hi> upon the diſcovery of the practice againſt His Life.</p>
            <p>That unhappy Prince, <hi>Rich.</hi> the 2. came young to His Crowne, and was check'd and over awed by the power of His Uncles, and other great Princes of His bloud, and imbroyled with the factions of a potent Nobility, who made the then aſſemblies of Parliament to act all their ambitious projects, &amp; ſorced the KING to entruſt powers to ſome of them, who thereby became Maſters of Him, and raiſed Forces againſt Him, and prevailed over Him; killed and deſtroyed divers of the KING'S moſt faithfull Subjects, enfonced Him to call this Parliament of 11. and proceeded tumultuouſly and rebelliouſly in it, and threatned to Depoſe the KING, unleſſe he conſented to make an Act to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teint and puniſh divers men that they accuſed of a Conſpiracy to deſtroy the KING (a known untruth,) but there is no mention that they were accuſed for aſſiſting the KING, making a Warre againſt the Parliament, there being no ſuch caſe; for it were a madneſſe to think the KING would make a Warre upon the Parliament (underſtood the Houſes) that He could Diſſolve them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46772:5"/>with His breath; nor any mention of fundamentall Lawes whereby ſuch caſe was Treaſon, ſo lewdly falſe are theſe Men in their Quotations: and in the ſame Parliament they got likewiſe a generall Pardon from the KING fot their proceedings upon this reaſon, <hi>That it was done for the Weale of the Kingdome,</hi> (that is in their opinions:) let any honeſt or knowing man that reads thoſe Records judge where the Treaſon lies, either in theſe that were thus pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or in others that were illegally deſtroyed: And when <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. being one of the chiefe Conſpirators againſt Him, and Depoſing Him, confirms in his Parliament after he had Impriſoned his lawfull KING, the acts of that lawleſſe Parliament, no man can think it other, then a meanes to aſſure his wicked Uſurpation and former Treaſon, and of no more authority, but of no uſe at all in the preſent queſtion.</p>
            <p>And if we had no clearer demonſtrations of thoſe mens corruptions, the uſe they make of this odious example might ſufficiently inſtruct all men of their intentions; and the ſad ſtory of the ſucceſſe of that deteſtable uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may warne us to prevent the progreſſe of theſe men; for from that yeare of the 11 of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, the Kingdome had no reſt for almoſt an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, conſtant faction among the Nobility; bloudy executions of ſuch perſons as the jealouſie of the Uſurper made him feare of; continuall Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and civill broyles at home, or warre abroad, and which ended not but in the finall extirpation of the numerous Male Line of <hi>our Kings,</hi> the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the very Famiſies of the greateſt part of the Nobility; beſides, the great change that fell on the minds of men, the Nation was grown barbarous, and the many inhumane cruelties and injuſtices that daily occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, may ſtrike horrour into any man of Honour, Piety, or Honeſty to thinke on ſuch a condition, which theſe Voters have in a great meaſure now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced.</p>
            <p>And for concluſion, they agree to the former Votes, and think that it is a double teſtimony, as the Stature of 11 <hi>Richard</hi> the 2. and, <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. and having ſerved themſelves of ridiculous complaints of the KING'S intentions, rumours of jealouſies and feares to begin this Warre upon Him, continue the ſame ſhameleſſe exclamations, when they have Impriſoned and Dethroned Him; and they may as well be believed, if they Vote that the KING is not in priſon, and that they have made no War againſt Him, as in Voting a Warre againſt them to deliver the KING, is a Warre againſt the Parliament. If they had made conſcience of Treaſon, theſe Votes had never been, nor this Warre. But they have gotten Force, and that's their Law; however it's to be hoped, that their Kingdome gotten by falſhood; and exerciſed by ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny will end ſuddenly, and then they will be as odious to themſelves, as they have been inſolent over others; and as they have <hi>Cain's</hi> curſe, will wiſh for his marke, leſt every one that meets them ſhould prove their Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> and re-printed at <hi>London.</hi> 1648.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46772:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
